Gaius Talcott Letters
Gaius Talcott Letters
1757-1771
Talcott, Gaius.
17 items (SC)
Letters of an American Quaker concerning spiritual matters.
149284
Biographical History
Gaius Talcott (b. 1736) was an American Quaker who lived in New Milford, Connecticut during the 18th century.
Talcott was born on November 2, 1736 to Hannah Ferriss and Nathan Talcott. His father died in 1738 and his mother was remarried to Dobson Wheeler around 1740. In 1766, Talcott married Sarah Caustin (or Causter), daughter of Sarah and Joseph Caustin (or Causter). The couple had two children, Joseph (b. 1768) and Hannah (1770-1791).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Gaius Talcott Letters consists of 17 letters. The collection contains both incoming and outgoing correspondence related to Gaius Talcott.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection contains one series, Correspondence, which is divided into two subseries: Incoming correspondence and Outgoing correspondence. Within each subseries, the material is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and philosophy; Talcott, Gaius.; Quakers -- United States.; Letters (correspondence)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming correspondence
    - 12 Sep 1766, initialed I. W. (Sc 289)
    - 05 Mar 1767, initialed M. W. (Sc 289)
    - 01 Jan 1769, initialed A. W. (Sc 289)
    - Undated
      - initialed M. M. (Sc 289)
      - initialed M. T. (Sc 289)
  - Outgoing correspondence
    - 03 Apr 1757, to Catherine Payton Ballitor (Sc 289)
      Gaius describes the simplicity of the Quaker marriage between Samuel Neal and Mary Peasley which took place on Friday, March 17, 1757. By March 26, Mary was dead of an appendicitis attack. Gaius then describes the funeral service at the meeting house and grave yard. Samuel says that Mary was diligent in her ministry since her return from America. (Note: Samuel may well be Samuel Bronson)
    - 20 Oct 1764, to Esteemed Friends Samuel and Elizabeth (Sc 289)
    - 24 Feb 1766, to Respected Friend, M. B. (Sc 289)
    - 03 May 1766, to Respected Friends (Sc 289)
    - 16 Jun 1766, to Respected Friends (Sc 289)
    - 29 Jun 1767, to Dear & Loving Friend (Sc 289)
    - 12 May 1771, to Dear Friend (Sc 289)
    - Undated
      - to My Dear & Esteemed Friend (Sc 289)
      - to Esteemed Friends Samuel & Elizabeth (Bronson) (Sc 289)
      - to Near & Loving Friend (Sc 289)
      - to My Friends (Sc 289)
      - to Near & Well Esteemed Friend, Address on verso is "To the care of Matthew Franklin at Stephen Fox, Rhode Island" (Sc 289)